<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook v4.4//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
  <artheader>
    <title>UMIT Network Inventory - Search</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Guilherme</firstname>
      <surname>Polo</surname>
      <copyright>
        <year>2007</year>
	<holder>Guilherme Polo</holder>
      </copyright>
    </author>
  </artheader>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>The Network Inventory search system is designed to find devices
    in Inventories. It searches based on Ports, Services, 
    Changes that happened, IP, MAC, Hostname, OS Match, OS Classes 
    and Fingerprint info.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Performing a search</title>
    <para>To search for something, just type whatever you want in the bar
    placed at the top of Network Inventory and hit 'Enter' or click on that
    icon search. Actually, to find devices it is important to follow some
    very important rules.</para>

    <para>To find devices based on port, you should search for something like
    this: port 80. Then it will search for devices containing port 80 in
    any state. If you want to search for devices containing only ports higher
    than 1024, you should do: port > 1024. The port syntax allows you to use
    the operators: '>', '&#060;', '==', '!=', '>=' and '&#060;='. But you
    can't use more than one at once.</para>

    <para>To find devices based on service, you should search for something
    like this: service apache. And will search for a service with that name.
    </para>

    <para>To find devices based on some change, you should search for something
    like this: change somechangetext.</para>

    <para>To search based on things like hostname, ip, and others, you just
    type the text. Searching devices by a valid ip is the fastest way to find
    them right now.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Bugs</title>

    <para>As your scan number grows in your Inventories, you will feel the
    pain when you try to search for devices. Also, you may get angry when
    you notice the search system is not really smart. And it may contain very
    ugly bugs right now. Now that you know all the bad news, you can hear
    the good ones =)</para>
    <para>The search will get smarter eventually, when pysqlite starts 
    supporting FTS (Full Text Search) on some new version. Things
    to attempt speeding up the results were not possible to be done 
    in time for Google Summer of Code 2007, but will be implemented
    as time and some other things allows.</para>
  </section>

</article>
